Hopansh Gahlot

+91-8791864585 | hopanshgahlot@gmail.com | LinkedIn | GitHub | Portfolio

Summary

Full Stack Developer with over 3 years of experience in the FinTech and SaaS industry. Skilled in React with strong capabilities in Node.js and Flask for back-end development. Experienced in using technology to solve complex challenges and create user-friendly solutions.

Work experience

Software Engineer - Pegasystems (Hyderabad)

November 2024 – Present

• Developing and maintaining scalable enterprise-level applications using React and the Pegasystems low-code application platform.

Associate Software Engineer 2 - Highradius (Hyderabad)

January 2024 – November 2024

- Developed a Chat-based Data Visualization & Support application using React and OpenAI
- Integrated **Retrieval augmented generation (RAG)** utility and **real-time chat functionality** with chatbot, reducing ticket volume by 30%

Associate Software Engineer 1 - Highradius (Hyderabad)

July 2022 - January 2024

- Enhanced the **Apache Superset** data visualization app by adding new charts with the help of **Echarts library**, increasing the variety of visualization components by 20%.
- Implemented RESTful APIs using Flask, facilitating integration between front-end and back-end systems.
- Engineered dashboard export and import functionalities, streamlining the creation process. This optimization eliminated 90% of redundant steps in dashboard development
- Wrote **Jest test suites**, leading to a 20% decrease in software defects and improved overall code quality.

Intern - Highradius (Bhubaneswar)

July 2021 – June 2022

- Contributed to 4+ web development projects using HTML, CSS, JavaScript, TypeScript, React, High-Charts, Material-UI and Node.js
- Gained experience with version control (git) and Agile methodologies
- Assisted in UI development for an AI-enabled B2B cloud application in the financial sector

Education

Bachelors of Technology in Information Technology,
Kalinga Institute of Industrial Technology, Bhubaneswar (2018 – 2022)

Skills

Frontend	HTML, CSS, JavaScript. TypeScript. React, Material UI, Ant Design
Backend	NodeJS, Python, Flask
Database	MySQL, MongoDB
DevOps	Docker, Git, GitHub Actions, Google Cloud Platform
Testing	Jest, React Testing Library

Projects

- ACADMIK: LLM-driven quiz and note creator built with React and Flask, leveraging the llama3-8B model.
- GIGGLE MATRIX: React app with Open-AI powered reverse image search using vector database.
- CHAT2CHART: Web app for creating charts from text prompts using React, Flask, and OpenAI.
- ED. ADDRESS: MERN stack web app for posting and finding tutoring services.
- CSS ARITH: TypeScript NPM library for arithmetic operations on CSS units

Achievements & Interests

- Intern of the Quarter: Q3 2021, Q2 2022
- Employee of the Quarter: Q2 2023
- Led a front-end development team on a high-impact project, ensuring successful delivery
- Enjoy portrait photography and digital art as hobbies